<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="devel">
  <title>Developing for SQO-OSS</title>
  <sect1 id="devel:arch">
    <title>Architectural Overview</title>
    <para></para>
    <sect2 id="devel:arch:tds">
      <title>Thin Data Access - TDS</title>
      <para>
        The TDA component processes data access requests that originate from either the
        FDA component or the Updater. The requests are abstracted versions of the
        requests that can be issued by programs used for accessing
        the data sources. All requests may only refer to a single project. Some examples
        are:
        <itemizedlist spacing='compact'>
            <listitem><para>"Checkout a specific Subversion (SVN) version."</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>"Get a diff between two SVN files"</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>"Get emails in mailing list X for the period starting on A and ending on B"</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>"Get all bugs after date X"</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        The TDA component implements three interfaces that group together operations
        based on the type of the target data source. There are different interfaces
        for accessing SVN repositories (SCMAccessor), mailing lists (MailingListAccessor),
        and bug management databases (BugDatabaseAccessor), which will be the primary
        sources of data for the SQO-OSS system. The TDA component groups together the
        implementations of these interfaces, in order to provide a single point of access for
        all of them.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="devel:arch:fds">
      <title>Fat Data Access - FDS</title>
      <para>
        The FDA is the component that all plug-ins use in order to retrieve data from the
        file repository. The FDA is an intelligent component; it knows about filegroups,
        project states and other conceptual organisations of the
        data that might arise. The FDA also combines data and metadata from the various
        data sources. All metric plug-ins talk to the FDA in order to get the required data for
        processing. Some example functions that this component will be able to carry out
        are the following:
        <itemizedlist spacing='compact'>
            <listitem><para>Get all artefacts affected by commit X</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Get the filegroup X for project state Y</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Get all emails sent by user X for mailing list Z</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Get all changes performed by user U between project states M and L</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        The FDA offers rich functionality and therefore should be able to represent
        various data formats. Data originating from only one data source will be represented
        using the datatypes exported by the TDA. Compound data will need special treat-
        ment: container objects are required to hold them. As the core functionality of
        the FDA mainly revolves around project states and file groups, we introduce the
        ProjectState and FileGroup containers, which contain placeholders for all basic
        data types. Additionally, the FDA will need read-only connections to the project
        metadata database in order to offer its functionality. Since the FDA is essentially a
        software library, each plug-in that uses it will initialise a connection to the metadata
        database, using the Alitheia Database Service.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="devel:arch:db">
      <title>Database Service</title>
      <para>
        Creating and handling connections to a database needs careful consideration.
        Typically, creating a connection to a database may take up more time than executing the
        actual data manipulation statements; moreover, databases set limits on the number
        of concurrent connections permissible. The database service should provide an
        efficient mechanism for creating, maintaining, and sharing connections among users.
        The mechanism should be thread-safe, as users will be asking for connections and
        using them through the same environment.
        The database service will therefore function as a connection pool. The connection
        pool will contain a configurable number of connections. A soft limit and a hard limit
        will also be configurable: upon reaching the soft limit, the number of connections
        to the database will be gradually increased, up to reaching the hard limit, after
        which new connections will be refused, until used connections are returned to the
        pool. Every service that needs access to the database will ask for a connection
        from the database service; the connection will be returned to the database service's
        connection pool when the service client does not use it any more.
        Since Alitheia assumes a concurrent usage model, the database service must pro-
        vide adequate transaction support. The database service will assume that the un-
        derlying database uses the serialisable isolation level. It will then provide calls by
        which other services can demarcate transactions; in particular, these will provide
        facilities for starting a transaction, for committing a transaction, and for rolling back
        a transaction.
      </para><para>
        The database service will require the type of the originator of each connection
        request as an input parameter. This will be useful for logging purposes and will
        also allow us to use different database servers for different uses.
        In addition to connectivity, the database service will offer programmatic access
        to the SQO-OSS metadata. Accessing a database from an application typically re-
        quires using Structured Query Language (SQL) statements. Different programming
        languages tackle the issue in different ways: for instance, in most C/C++ programs
        some form of embedded SQL is used; in Perl, and other scripting languages, one
        uses libraries that pass strings containing SQL statements to the database; in Java,
        one uses the Java Database Connectivity (JDBC) Application Programming Interface
        (API) to the same end.
      </para><para>
        That means that while the bulk of the application may be written in one language
        (Java, in SQO-OSS), non-trivial parts of it have to be written in SQL. Mixing the two
        languages can be ugly and messy. Moreover, Java developers may not be particularly
        proficient in SQL, and vice versa. Most importantly, the particular SQL statements
        and syntax may vary depending on the chosen database, which entails decrease in
        portability. Alitheia gets around this problem by encapsulating all system database
        related functionality inside the database service.
      </para><para>
        For these reasons all access to the system database from the rest of the SQO-
        OSS system will be from special Java classes. These classes will broadly follow the
        Data Access Object (DAO) design pattern. In our case, we will take DAOs as
        classes that encapsulate the interaction with the data source. Hence, for each table
        we will have one class. An instance of such a class
        will contain the data of a particular row of the table. Static methods of the class
        will allow queries to the table. Queries that return data from joined tables will be
        implemented in one of the related classes and will return the queried data detached
        from the result sets originally returned by the query mechanism.
        Note that Alitheia comprises a system database
        which is independent from the actual measurements carried out and database
        schemata that correspond to such measurements. To anticipate that discussion, a plug-in
        that is responsible for carrying out a specific measurement is responsible for storage
        and retrieval operations of the measurements. As we cannot know in advance the
        individual database schema it would require, it is responsible for defining
        manipulating its own database schema. Still, every plug-in will use the database connectivity
        service for handling access to the database, and will allow access to its measurement
        data through a DAO level of abstraction, as is the case for the system database per
        se.
      </para><para>
        The methods startDBSession(), commitDBSession(), rollbackDBSession(), isDBSessionActive()
        are used to control the connection to the database and the DAOs.
        Basically, all the queries, DAO manipulation, and insertions/deletions have to
        happen within a database session, which you can see as a connection to the
        database with a transaction open.
        startDBSession() is the method that starts a new session, and commitDBSession()
        and rollbackDBSession() end it, either by committing the modifications in the
        database or just discarding them.
        Finally, isDBSessionActive() tells you if a session is currently opened or not.
        The DAOs remain "connected" as long as the session is open,
        meaning they will load collections and properties and automatically persist
        changes you make to them (provided you commit the changes at the end of the
        session).
        Note that you can still access loaded DAOs even after the database session was
        closed, but lazy-loading won't work and modifications won't be saved, even if
        you open a new database session. In other words, DAOs belong to the session that
        created them only.
      </para><para>
        Another important thing is that the DBService is thread-safe. this means you can safely
        call all of its methods simultaneously from multiple threads without risks of
        race conditions or weird behaviour.
        In particular, each thread has its own session, so the modifications you make in
        your session aren't affecting sessions in other threads, especially as opening a
        session automatically starts a database transaction, meaning the database is
        locked for your thread only. (note: this means you should be VERY careful about
        always properly closing a session and keeping them as short as possible).
      </para><para>
        Finally, exceptions are not used for simplicity's sake.
        Instead, methods like addRecord or deleteRecord return a boolean value
        indicating success or not. For queries and the find methods,
        null/emptyCollection will be returned in case of an error. The important thing
        to know is that Hibernate requires a session to be closed as soon as an
        exception is thrown from its code, which means in some cases your session might
        be automatically closed during a method call. If you need to make the
        difference between no result returned or an error that occured, you can use
        isDBSessionActive()).
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="devel:arch:pa">
      <title>Plug-in Administrator</title>
      <para></para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="devel:arch:updater">
      <title>Updater</title>
      <para></para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="devel:plugins">
    <title>Developing Plugins</title>
    <para>
      In this section, we provide an overview of how plug-ins work in
      Alitheia.
    </para>
    <sect2 id="devel:plugins:quick">
      <title>Quick and dirty guide</title>
      <para>
        To follow the instructions replace:
        <itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <command>$ALITHEIA</command>
              with path where you unbundled or checked out the Alitheia
              source code distribution.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <command>$YOURMETRIC</command>
              with the symbolic name of you metric
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        Then, you do:
        <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <command>
                svn cp $ALITHEIA/metrics/skeleton
                $ALITHEIA/metrics/$YOURMETRIC
              </command>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Change the name of the packages:
              <itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    <classname>
                      eu.sqooss.impl.metrics.skeleton
                    </classname>
                    to
                    <classname>
                      eu.sqooss.impl.metrics.$YOURMETRIC
                    </classname>
                  </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    <classname>eu.sqooss.metrics.skeleton</classname>
                    to
                    <classname>eu.sqooss.metrics.$YOURMETRIC</classname>
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Change the name of the classes:
              <itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    <classname>
                      eu.sqooss.impl.metrics.skeleton.SkeletomImplemenation
                    </classname>
                    to
                    <classname>

eu.sqooss.impl.metrics.$YOURMETRIC.$YOURMETRICImplementation
                    </classname>
                  </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    <classname>
                      eu.sqooss.impl.service.SkeletonActivator
                    </classname>
                    to
                    <classname>
                      eu.sqooss.impl.service.$YOURMETRICActivator
                    </classname>
                  </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    <classname>
                      eu.sqooss.metrics.skeleton.Skeleton
                    </classname>
                    to
                    <classname>
                      eu.sqooss.metrics.$YOURMETRIC.$YOURMETRIC
                    </classname>
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Add the required interfaces to the definition of the
              <classname>
                eu.sqooss.metrics.$YOURMETRIC.$YOURMETRIC
              </classname>
              interface
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Implement one job for each metric your plug-in calculates.
              This can be performed by copying the class
              <classname>
                eu.sqooss.metrics.skeleton.SkeletonJob
              </classname>
              to
              <classname>
                eu.sqooss.metrics.$YOURMETRIC.$YOURMETRICJob
              </classname>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Implement the required
              <methodname>getResult(*)</methodname>
              and
              <methodname>run(*)</methodname>
              methods in the class
              <classname>
                eu.sqooss.impl.metrics.$YOURMETRIC.$YOURMETRICImplementation
              </classname>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Change the following entries in the manifest file (
              <filename>$ALITHEIA/metrics/$YOURMETRIC/manifest</filename>)
              to much your metric
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Bundle-SymbolicName</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Bundle-Activator</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Bundle-Description</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Bundle-Name</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Modify the <filename>pom.xml</filename> to match your
              metric configuration
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
      If you follow these steps closely, you will have a metric bundle
      that can be loaded in Alitheia, start its own metric jobs and
      retrieve results from the database. All you need to do now is to
      implement the <methodname>run()</methodname> method in each
      metric job.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
    <title>Developing plug-ins</title>
    <sect3 id="devel:plugins:defs">
      <title>Definitions</title>
      <para>Following is a list of definitions of common terms in the
      context of SQO-OSS</para>
      <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
          <term>Plugin</term>
          <listitem>
              <para>
                  An OSGi bundle that implements and exports the
                  <classname>eu.sqooss.service.abstactmetric.AlitheiaPlugin
                  </classname>
                  interface
              </para>
          </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
          <term>Asset</term>
          <listitem>
              <para>
                  A collection of development data, such as a source code
                  repository, a mailing list or a bug managemnet database
              </para>
          </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
          <term>Project</term>
          <listitem>
              <para>
                  A set of assets consisting of at least a Subversion
                  repository and additionally a collection of mailing
                  lists and a bug management system
              </para>
          </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
          <term>Metric</term>
          <listitem>
              <para>
                  An algorith that evaluates a property of a project
                  asset or a change in a project asset and returns a result
              </para>
          </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="devel:plugins:general">
      <title>General</title>
      <para>
          <itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>
          <listitem>
            <para>
                Plugins define one or more metrics. A metric operates on
                a project asset and produces results.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
                Metrics can produce an arbitrary set of results per evaluated
                project asset. Metric results can be of arbitrary datatypes.
                Metric results always have a mime type attached.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
                The result of a metric calculation is stored in the database.
                The Alitheia system provides a default storage facility for
                metrics for each one of the evaluated project assets. The
                default storage facility can only store a single value for
                each metric per evaluated resource type. However, plug-ins are
                free to implement custom DB tables for intermediate or final
                results, provided that the final results are associated with
                the project asset on which the metric operated.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="devel:plugins:activation">
      <title>Plugin Activation</title>
      <para>
          Each plug-in is associated with a set of activation types. An
          activation type indicates that a plug-in should be activated to
          evaluate new project data when the corresponding project assets have
          been updated. Also, the plug-in can only return metric results
          for the supported activation types. An activation type is essentially
          the class type for the DAO that represents the asset type that the
          plug-in defined metrics can evaluate.
      </para>
      <para>
          Currently, the supported activation types are the following:
      <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
          <term><classname>StoredProject</classname></term>
          <listitem>
              <para>
                  Project wide activations. Plug-ins
                  implementing this activation type are triggered when
                  a new project is added to the system. Metrics might
                  can use this activation type to store project wide
                  results
              </para>
          </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
          <term><classname>ProjectVersion</classname></term>
          <listitem>
              <para>
                  Per-version activations. Metrics are activated when the
                  a new project version is commited to the source code
                  repository.
              </para>
          </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
          <term><classname>ProjectFile</classname></term>
          <listitem>
              <para>
                  Per-file activations. Metrics are activated when a project
                  file has been added, changed or removed from the source code
                  repository.
              </para>
          </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
          <term><classname>FileGroup</classname></term>
          <listitem>
              <para>
                  Per-filegroup activations. Metrics are activated when
                  the file group has changed, e.g. a when a file was modified
                  in a regular expression based file group.
              </para>
          </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      More activation types will be supported as the corresponding subsystems
      continue to develop.
      </para>
      <para>
          To denote their support for an activation type, plug-ins must implement
          one or more of the interfaces residing under <classname>
          eu.sqooss.service.abstractmetric</classname>.
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="devel:plugins:iface">
      <title>The AlitheiaPlugin interface</title>
      <para>
      <programlisting>
public interface AlitheiaPlugin {
    String getVersion();
    String getAuthor();
    Date getDateInstalled();
    String getName();
    String getDescription();
    Result getResult(DAObject o, List&lt;Metric&gt; l)
        throws MetricMismatchException;
    void run(DAObject o)
        throws MetricMismatchException;
    boolean update();
    boolean install();
    boolean remove();
    String getUniqueKey();
    List &lt;Class&lt;? extends DAObject&gt;&gt; getActivationTypes();
    List&lt;PluginConfiguration&gt; getConfigurationSchema();
}
      </programlisting>
    </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="devel:plugins:implscr">
      <title>Implementing a plug-in from scratch</title>
      <para></para>
    </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
