<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="pref">
<title>Preface</title>
<sect1 id="pref:whatis">
    <title>What is SQO-OSS?</title>
    <para>
    SQO-OSS is a project that aims at
implementing a quality-checking system that can be used by Open Source software
projects to gather information about the quality of their code and relate this
information to other data sources such as issue-tracker data and mailinglist
archives. SQO-OSS can be utilised for management-level information to assess
various aspects of a software project, such as developer productivity. The system
is also useful for developers that want to use static source code analysis
to improve the code.
    </para>


<para>
SQO-OSS is funded through the European Union
and will be released under a Free Software license
in late 2008. The platform will be deployed
in a central location for processing a number of
large projects; having quality evaluations
of many Open Source projects
in one place enables easier comparison of the
quality of different projects.
Individual Open Source projects are encouraged
to deploy the Alitheia system for their local
quality control and evaluation processes.
Because of the architecture of the Alitheia system,
the system scales up from relatively modest hardware
checking a single project to distributed hardware
supporting hundreds of projects and users.
</para>


</sect1>
<sect1 id="pref:alitheia">
    <title>What is Alitheia?</title>

<para>
Alitheia is the name of a platform,
developed by the SQO-OSS project,
for the automated objective evaluation of the quality
of Open Source projects.
By analyzing both the soft and the hard project
artifacts (the project source code history is "hard"
while the mailing lists, bug tracker entries
and other human communications are "soft")
the Alitheia software will produce a broader
and more comprehensive picture of the quality
and viability of each Open Source project than tools that
examine only the product of the project.
</para>


<para>The name Alitheia was chosen for its Greek roots
(the majority of the project is executed in Greece).
In ancient Greek, the term stands for "neat and businesslike
truth."
The Alitheia system does indeed intend to deliver the neat
and businesslike truth
about Open Source projects.
By evaluating the quality --- captured in
measurements of many different aspects of quality
and aggregated through the SQO-OSS quality model ---
of Open Source projects
over time it becomes possible to compare and contrast
different projects, but most importantly gives the
contributors to the projects an idea of how their
own quality is developing.
</para>




</sect1>
<sect1 id="pref:hist">
    <title>A bried history of SQO-OSS</title>
    <para></para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="pref:conventions">
    <title>Conventions</title>
    <para></para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="pref:info">
    <title>Further Information</title>
    <para></para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="pref:involve">
    <title>Getting involved</title>
    <para></para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="pref:bugrep">
    <title>Bug Reporting</title>
    <para></para>
</sect1>
</chapter>
