<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="pref">
<title>Preface</title>
<sect1 id="pref:whatis">
    <title>What is SQO-OSS?</title>
    <para>
    SQO-OSS is a project funded by the European Community that aims at
implementing a quality-checking system that can be used by Open Source software
projects to gather information about the quality of their code and relate this
information to other data sources such as issue-tracker data and mailinglist
archives. SQO-OSS can be utilised for management-level information to assess
various aspects of a software project, such as developer productivity. The system
is also useful for developers that want to use static source code analysis
to improve the code.
    </para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="pref:alitheia">
    <title>What is Alitheia?</title>
    <para>
    Alitheia is the name of the software that is produced by the SQO-OSS
project. Alitheia core accesses different data source, currently version control
repositories, mailing list archives and issue tracker databases. This data can
be analysed using plugins written in Java, Python or C++. Plugins parse the
various datasources extracting information and storing it in a relational
database. Those plugins and data sources can be configured using a webinterface,
called webadmin. Alitheia supports different front-ends for displaying the data.
Currently, there is a web interface that displays the results of the plugins,
and an extension for the Eclipse IDE that imports data directly into the context
of development.
    </para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="pref:hist">
    <title>A bried history of SQO-OSS</title>
    <para></para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="pref:conventions">
    <title>Conventions</title>
    <para></para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="pref:info">
    <title>Further Information</title>
    <para></para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="pref:involve">
    <title>Getting involved</title>
    <para></para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="pref:bugrep">
    <title>Bug Reporting</title>
    <para></para>
</sect1>
</chapter>
