<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="user">
<title>User Manual</title>
<sect1 id="user:interfaces">
    <title>Interfaces</title>
    <para>
    The Alitheia system is built with independence from user interfaces in mind, so it
    can in theory have any kind of user interface on top of it. Currently, two user
    interfaces, each with a different purpose are existing for Alitheia -- the WebUI, a
    user interface running in a webbrowser and therefore being very easily accessible,
    and the Eclipse plugin, an add-on for the Eclipse IDE that integrates quality
    measurements seamlessly into a development environment. The user interfaces
    exchange data with the Alitheia core through a well-defined web service interface.
    </para>
    <sect2  id="user:interfaces:web" >
        <title>Web</title>
        <para>
        The WebUI runs on top of the Tomcat application server. It is implemented
        as a set of Java beans and JSP (Java Server Pages) that display projects
        that have been evaluated by the Alitheia system and their results.
        </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2  id="user:interfaces:eclipse">
        <title>Eclipse</title>
        <para>
        The main goal of the Eclipse IDE plug-in is to help developers keep track of the
        quality of projects, that they develop in an Eclipse programming environment. The
        plug-in provides easy access to quality evaluation results, calculated on the fly from
        the underlying SQO-OSS framework.
        </para>
        <para>
        The Eclipse IDE plug-in is distributed in form of standard application plug-in. For
        activating it, the user has to copy the plug-in into the Eclipse plug-ins tree and
        restart Eclipse, if it is already running. In the recent version of the Eclipse IDE (since
        v.3.4M6) the user can also install the plug-in from the Software Updates menu.
        </para>
        <para>
        The plug-in functionality is available per project scope and accessible via exten-
        sion to the Properties context menu (Alt+Enter). The above mentioned menu
        extension is enabled for any component of the project, but the plug-in itself is active
        only for a limited set of project resources. The list of resources allows only entities
        that can be potentially evaluated by a SQO-OSS framework and includes:
        <itemizedlist spacing='compact'>
            <listitem><para>source file -- as data entity, capable for quality evaluation</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>source folder -- as a resource group</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>the project -- as a global entity</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        The user accessible functionality of the Eclipse IDE plugin is split into three
        different views available in the menu extension's tree:
        <itemizedlist spacing='compact'>
            <listitem><para>configuration view node</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>profile view node</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>quality view node.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>
        The configuration view node is shared between all project's resources. Its main
        purpose is to let the user enter, validate and save the settings required for estab-
        lishing a connection with the selected SQO-OSS framework. This view also handles
        invalid connection settings and can notify the user in case of unavailable framework.
        In the last case, the specified connection settings can be stored and validated later
        on, when a connection can be established. Both other views will be disabled until a
        successful connection to a SQO-OSS framework is established.
        </para>
        <para>
        The profile view node allows the user to create, modify or remove evaluation
        profiles. An evaluation profile encapsulates a group of projects resources (mostly
        source files in a selected source tree or subtree), allows resource filtering (e.g. per
        implementation language) and where applicable can trigger an evaluation event from
        the SQO-OSS framework.
        </para>
        <para>
        The quality view node contains the actual metric evaluation results. Its main
        purpose is to retrieve evaluation information from the attached SQO-OSS framework
        depending on the selected resource and metric, and then display the evaluation
        results in a proper way. In addition, this view allows comparison with a previous
        version of the selected resource.
        </para>
    </sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="user:plugins">
    <title>Plug-ins and Measurements</title>
    <para></para>
    <sect2 id="user:plugins:wc">
        <title>WC plugin</title>
        <para></para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="user:plugins:contrib">
        <title>Contributing plugin</title>
        <para></para>
    </sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>
